a Sinister laugh pierces The Silence of the African Savannah soon joined by the
sounds of Flesh tearing and Bones being pulverized haunting arched back
creatures Dart around their meal ripping it apart with their enormous Jaws in
just 25 minutes an entire zebra is devoured skin Hooves bones teeth and all
only a pool of blood Remains the spotted hyena is the most
numerous large predator in Africa with an estimated 27,000 to 47,000
individuals living in the wild their habitat includes all types of
environments such as forests swamps mountains and deserts and their
reputation among humans wherever they may be is largely negative they're often
seen as ugly cowardly and gluttonous the evil cronies who helped scar kill
Mufasa the Shady llies who lurk in the shadows waiting for an opportunity to
steal a more noble animals meal their cackling is unsettling and their large
teeth punched over figure and darting movements are menacing but hyenas are so
much more than just creepy they are remarkably intelligent and extremely
effective Hunters largely because they don't operate
alone they live in clans of six to over 100 individuals larger than any Wolfpack
lion pride or orcapod and these groupings aren't just a bunch of
individuals who happen to coexist near each other these Clans are incredibly
sophisticated and their social structure is unlike that of any other carnivore
but sophisticated doesn't mean Pleasant the lives of spotted hyenas are filled
with brutal and constant competition with other members of their Clan to even
get a chance at eating a meal a spotted hyena must prove its dominance over the
others again and again and for the males this is even more difficult because
females always dominate them and while a matriarchal group of animals is not
unheard of it gets even weirder female hyenas are not just in charge they've
also evolved so that their genitals look almost exactly like male genitalia they
urinate mate and even give birth through this pseudo penis why do hyenas live in
such big groups when these groups are filled with constant fighting why are
the females in charge and why did their reproductive organs evolve to be
indistinguishable from a
males of the four species of hyena the spotted or laughing hyena is the largest
and while most people compare hyenas to dogs they actually have more in common
genetically with cats and are even more closely related to mongooses and civits
and the size of a spotted hyena might surprise you they are not the scraggly
little muts Disney makes them out to be they're actually as large or larger than
wolves weighing up to 86 kg or 190 lb and reaching 1.8 m in length and for its
size the spotted hyena has one of the strongest skulls of any carnivore hyid
are the only existing animal who evolved to crack bones with their jaws and
spotted hyenas are the top among them their bite can exert a pressure of 80 kg
Force per square cm or 1,140 PSI which is 40% more Force than a
lion can generate and 15% more than a grizzly bear wild hyenas have even been
seen cracking open giraffe femur which measure 7 cm in diameter the teeth of a
spotted hyena are built exactly for this the upper and lower third Prem molers
are enormous conical bone Crushers compare this to an African lion it's a
voracious Predator but does not have the bone crushing molers that a hyena does
in addition to this the spotted hyena has a pronounced sagittal Crest to which
extremely strong jaw muscles are attached this bone cracking ability
allows them to take advantage of a food source that is inaccessible to most
animals but they weren't always so formidable before the spotted hyena
diverged from the striped and brown hyenas 10 million years ago its direct
ancestor would have been a smaller scavenger type hyena that could maybe
Crush some bones but not take down massive prey but at one point in their
evolution spotted hyenas developed sharp caracals behind their crushing premolar
teeth that cut through tough skin like scissors these teeth becoming bigger and
sharper meant the hyenas no longer had to wait for their prey to die to eat it
as is the case with solitary scavengers like the brown hyena they had evolved to
become social Hunters unlike other types of hyenas spotted hyenas kill about 95%
of their food themselves scientists have ranked their hunting abilities on par
with that of lions and cheetahs their large bodies likely evolved as a result
of the transition from Scavenging to hunting scavenger hyenas tend to be
smaller to use less energy while covering great distances in order to
find a meal whereas social Hunters need to be bigger to take down large prey but
that's not to say hyenas can't travel great distances and travel fast they
extra long front legs let them run at speeds up to 60
kmph chasing down prey for sometimes kilomet at a time the size of their prey
depends on if they're hunting alone or in a group while solo they'll go after
smaller animals like birds rabbits porcupines and fish as their numbers
grow they choose bigger and bigger pre from gazel and warthogs to Buffalo and
even young rhinos once they catch their meal spotted hyenas give out their
characteristic laugh to alert their Clan and the feasting begins within minutes
entire animals are consumed and although they are primarily Hunters hyenas don't
discriminate when it comes to their food source they've been seen eating bugs
like termites and caterpillars and also rotting putrid flesh that other animals
refuse to eat and yet they don't even get sick from it they happily eat
Anthrax infected carcasses and are unaffected by infectious disease
outbreaks like rabies and distemper which have killed many lions and wild
dogs one way they fight off these potentially deadly microbes is by having
an incredibly acidic stomach herbivores who don't eat risky meat have a stomach
pH of 4 to 6 many carnivores who try to stick to fresh meat have a stomach pH of
3.6 and a hyena stomach pH is less than two this High concentration of
hydrochloric acid decimates most bacteria before it can do any damage
hyenas also have a relatively short digestive tract which prevents bacteria
from lingering too long hyenas also likely pass small doses of pathogens
around as they groom eat and compete with each other which may help build up
group-wide immunity to toxins like Anthrax and on top of this they have
naturally high levels of antibodies but not all spotted hyenas
have the same amount the higher the social status a spotted hyena has the
more antibodies they carry such hyenas are better fed and spend less energy on
hunting and nursing injuries lower ranked hyenas do not get such luxuries
and it's not just antibody levels that are at stake when it comes to the social
order of hyenas in a hyena Clan everything comes down to
rank spotted hyena Clans have the most rigid hierarchy structure of any social
mammal and it really pays to be on top in addition to Better Health a higher
rank means more food stronger allies and the right to reproduce and in a clan of
spotted hyenas females are always in charge physically female spotted hyenas
are larger than males by as much as 20 kg they're also stronger and arguably
meaner at the top of the group is the alpha female when she has Cubs they're
ranked right beneath her and as they grow up their cubs are ranked beneath
them and so on daughters usually remain in their birth Clan For Life and build
close relationships with their mothers and sisters one grouping of of mothers
and daughters is known as a matrilineal group separate matrilineal groups often
join together creating one massive Clan these kin groups are organized within
the clan by the dominance level of their oldest female but unfortunately for
males their place is always at the bottom the life of a male hyena may
start out okay if he's born to a high ranking female but this is shortlived
males are only allowed to stay with their families for around 2 to 3 years
after that they leave the clan they're born into and beg for admittance into a
new one if accepted they will rank absolute last after all females and
their cubs and after other males who joined the clan before them they are
known as immigrant males and their life basically sucks they're forced to live
on the outskirts are the last to eat if there's even anything left
and have absolutely no say in when or with who they get to mate they are
generally riddled with injuries have worn down teeth from chewing on too many
bones and live half as long as females while the life of a female isn't nearly
as Bleak it's endlessly competitive while males are known appeasers during
conflict to avoid losing what little status they have females are much more
aggressive and are constantly picking fights to gain or keep their rank Clans
are usually stable for many years but if any of the top ranking females die peace
is no longer guaranteed a coalition of the lower ranking females May topple the
alpha female Coalition from the throne females will even kill each other's Cubs
to maintain their social standing and to cut their Rivals Bloodlines short in one
study that looked at deaths of cubs under Oney old 21 out of 99 of them
could be attributed to infanticide Always by female Killers many times the
killer was even related to the Cubs she murdered even litter mates have to
compete sometimes to the death most litters have two Cubs which fight for
the right to nurse first Sometimes one Cub will end up killing their weaker
sibling half of young hyenas die before reaching maturity so why do hyenas
bother living together if there's so much risk because whether they like it
or not they need each other because while the risk from hyenas within their
own Clan is high the risk from other clans of hyenas or Prides of lions is
even higher they need each other to defend themselves and their kills and to
take down large prey and those immigrant males who all the females seem to hate
they too are recruited to help with hunting or fighting and these hyena
Clans however dysfunctional are extremely effective they've been
observed defending territories of up to 620 square mil or, 1600 square km from
outside threats a single hyena could not defeat a lion but a clan of hyenas
absolutely can hyenas are the only thing lions are regularly seen running from
but as soon as the prey is killed or outside threat is nullified hyenas
within the same Clan do try to keep their distance from one another to
reduce the chances of Confrontation this Arrangement is known
as a fishion fusion Society individuals come together when needed and then
disperse as soon as possible and maintaining this Arrangement requires
sophisticated communication skills spotted hyenas have one of the richest
vocal repertoar of any terrestrial mammal their laugh sounds Sinister but
is actually a sign of excitement fear or frustration and their whooping call
conveys a wealth of information to their clanmates it's a haunting sound that can
travel up to 3 miles transporting with it information about the color including
its identity sex and age hyenas can even count how many calls they are hearing a
useful tool when trying to gauge whether to fight a rival gang
hyenas live and die by the clan a clan ruled by females a clan whose
cooperation breeds competition but there's one more thing about spotted
hyenas that's just downright strange the reproductive organs of a female spotted
hyena look almost exactly like a male's and scientists don't really know
why the reproductive organs of female spotted hyenas are unlike any other
animal even other hyena species they have an unusually long clitoris
resembling a penis it's been classified as a pseudo penis or peniform clitoris
and is used to urinate mate and give birth they also have a fused and
enlarged labia resembling a scrotum this atypical Anatomy has caused researchers
to misgender female spotted hyenas as male only to discover the truth when
they've later given birth this unusual Anatomy means they're the only mammal to
lack a vaginal opening which makes mating and birthing very difficult to
mate a female retracts the pseudo penis in on itself kind of like pushing up the
sleeve on your shirt and creates an opening into which the male inserts his
own penis and while this may be difficult there's one benefit that's
clear it gives the female hyenas complete control over who they mate with
because penetration is impossible without their cooperation but even when
mating does occur the chances of successful reproduction is low Hyena's
reproductive Canal is twice as long as a similarly sized animals and includes a
hair pin turn making it an incredible difficult Journey for sperm traveling to
the uterus and and for Cubs during birth for first time mothers living in
captivity about 60% of their cubs die most often from Suffocation while
getting stuck in the birth canal these challenges have made scientists wonder
why spotted highas have evolved in this way since reproduction is essential for
survival of the species why has their Anatomy developed in such a way that
makes it so difficult it all comes back to competition there their large skulls
jaws and teeth are what makes spotted hyenas able to crush bones which lets
them outperform other Predators but growing these features takes several
years so in order for young hyenas to survive long enough to develop them
hyena mothers nurse their cubs for around 14 months and help them get
enough food even after they're weaned until they're three or four this means
it's in the interest of the species for birth rates to be lower than other types
of Predator why extra babies have to die in the birth canal or fight each other
to the death instead of simply not being conceived in the first place I don't
know the theme of hyena life seems to be brutality at every turn but as ruthless
as it all seems so much of what hyenas are fighting for is to keep their cubs
alive hyenas are very caring mothers when their cubs die they are distraught
and they do everything in their power to protect them and keep them safe the
reputation of hyenas as creepy selfish scavengers is largely misplaced while
their lives are Rife with hardship and competition their capacity for
cooperation is unrivaled in the world of predators and their place among the
predators of Africa is not lowly behind the Cheetahs leopards and lions if
anything clans of hyenas are the top among them all no one knows spotted
hyenas better than the people who study them in the field and of them no one is
more well-versed than expert biologist and animal behaviorist K whole Camp I
was lucky enough to snag an interview with her to get the inside story about
what it's like to study these amazing creatures in the wild and our main
research tools are a pair of binoculars and a notebook we can watch them from
about this far away it's just a blast being in the field with spotted hyenas
for so long Dr Hull Camp has seen a huge array of personalties ities and it's
impossible to not form attachments to certain individuals my favorite hyena of
all time was a hyena named cois and she was really curious a very smart hyena
and she figured out that she could go catch a gazelle and she could do it in
the presence of all these other hyenas and then she would bring it right over
and put it right down next to the tire but nobody else would come that close to
the car and she figured this out right away but life in the bush is dangerous
you know she I saw her get bitten in the face by a big Cobra once he had two
puncture wounds on either side of her nose nose and they started welling up
blood and I thought oh no you know she's going to die now and she staggered off
into the bushes and I didn't ever expect to see her again but a couple days later
she comes out of their bushes and she's looking just fine so her stories about
how these animals defy death at every turn are incredible and she explains
what humans stand to learn from their near invincibility but working in the
field is no Cakewalk either and hearing her stories about the dangers she and
her team face spending months the field in Kenya are riveting and most of all I
love doing interviews like this to learn what it's actually like to do the
research that I talk about here on YouTube for everyone who dreams of one
day being a biologist interviews like these with Dr hul Camp shine a light on
the wild adventure that such a career entails to watch the full unedited
interview head over to nebula and find it under the real science field notes
page nebula is a streaming platform that we built for exactly this reason to
explore topics more deeply sometimes in new formats like this interview nebula
allows me to take risks like this and experiment more whether it's this
extended interview or the nebula original series I made called becoming
human about the incredible story of how we came to understand human evolution
nebula is a place for all of its creators to make experimental and new
content like Joe Scott's Mysteries of the human body which takes you through
some of the the most baffling diseases and epidemics from history or Wendover
Productions extremities which shows you why and how people live in Earth's most
isolated and extreme settlements nebula has even produced a featurelength film
called night of the coconut and a genre bending award-winning play called the
prince which you can watch in its entirety on nebula and now if you sign
up with the link below subscribers also get access to classes you can watch
dozens of in-depth classes of creators teaching you how to create so if you
sign up using the link below you can support this channel directly and get
both nebula and nebula classes for 40% off the annual plan for just $30 for the
entire
year