for as long as humans have been building civilizations
we've been reliant on one very special ecosystem from Egypt to China to
Mesopotamia many of our most ancient cities depended on the river ecosystem
for food water and transportation even now in modern times
rivers are among the most economically and ecologically important ecosystems
around welcome back explorers in this special
two-part adventure we'll be learning all about the river ecosystem including what
characteristics to find these places what organisms we can find here and why
they matter to you and me in this first part we'll be looking at River structure
information and in the second part we'll be looking at River food chains these
are some of my absolute favorite places to go exploring so let's jump right in
and learn about the river ecosystem even the largest rivers start with a network
of smaller Springs streams and creeks called tributaries which eventually
connect to create one large flow many of these smaller tributaries are like mini
rivers of their own and are much easier to study in film we'll be using this
tributary of the ad controller to learn about the abiotic or nonliving
components of the river ecosystem to start with it's important that we know
how rivers are defined for one thing rivers contain flowing water in usually
lots of it most rivers have a clearly defined
channel where the water flows as well as river banks which are dry areas of land
on either side of the channel the actual course of the river may change over time
but these two key components are nearly always present both provide important
habitat for many plants and animals as the water that makes up rivers and their
tributaries flows across the landscape it picks up components of the
terrestrial ecosystems that it passes through this means that rivers often
contain a wide variety of soils minerals nutrients and organic matter from many
different locations these new materials being added to
rivers can be a very important part of their ecology ensuring that there's
enough nutrients to support the complex food chains which we find here however
this also means that any pollutants or silts can get into the water from
surrounding areas and contaminate the entire ecosystem pollutants can include
toxins such as arsenic or lead which are dangerous for both aquatic organisms and
humans or silts which cloud up the water and block sunlight from reaching the
organisms living in it we call the process by which water picks up and
moves materials erosion we can clearly see erosion when walk at places on the
riverbank like this where it looks like the loggers cutting into the ground now
over long periods of time erosion is the process that creates huge geological
features such as canyons deposition is when materials that have been picked up
by the water are then placed somewhere else usually when the water slows down
we can see an example of deposited materials right here where the water has
slowed down and left lots of sand behind both erosion and deposition are
processes that have huge impacts on how River ecosystems look and how the
organisms in them live they can also have serious consequences on human
behavior because who wants to build a house somewhere that is being eroded
away by a river that's one of the reasons that we are constantly tracking
where water is flowing in what impact it is having on the land around it
every drop of water that falls from the sky as precipitation will eventually
make its way to a river by tracking where the water in a certain area ends
up we can map out an area call the watershed all the water in this location
will find its way to a specific River and eventually the ocean understanding
watersheds is very important because if we don't know where the water in a river
is coming from we have no idea where pollutants or new species can be coming
from watersheds are usually huge covering hundreds of miles of land
that means that our river systems are taking in huge amounts of material as
they flow throughout the landscape even if a piece of trash isn't directly
dumped in a river by me or you it still ends up there either during a rainfall
event or by getting washed into a tributary the study of water and how it
moves is known as hydrology and is just as important as ecological studies when
dealing with a river ecosystem if you don't understand how rivers form and
what makes them unique it is difficult to understand why the organisms found
within these systems look in act the way they do the most important things to
remember from today's episode or that rivers are areas of moving water with a
clearly defined channel and stream banks in that they contain pieces of all the
terrestrial ecosystems around them and the second part of this video we'll be
taking a look at River food chains a meeting so with incredible plants and
animals that we can find here until then stay curious and keep adventuring
everywhere this is Benzino of the wild report signing out