[Music] why is it so hard
for people to understand this really basic concept
if you want to win and you want to guarantee that you are going to get
where you want to get
everybody wants to guarantee that's why they ask so many questions you know they
say how long is it going to take what's the best way to get here what's
this what's that and they analyze all these different things
and they try to come up with this college auditorium size blackboard full
of formulas and graphs and all these things that are going to make
us more successful they're going to get us the respect that
we're looking for the recognition that we look for
we try to plan all of these things out and the problem is for most people as
they come to a point where they are overwhelmed by the information
[Music] and every once in a while you've just
got a bottom line what's the bottom line here
and the bottom line for you and the bottom line for me and the bottom line
for every other on this planet is really simple
if you want to be great if you want to get the recognition if you want to get
paid if you want all of the things that you dream about there is
only one way to guarantee that you will have those things only one
and that is becoming so good at what you do no matter what it is you do
that is undeniable that other people recognize how great you are
it's a character trait that you develop that means any place that you
are put you will put in the work you will learn the skills you will improve
your arsenal to become
the undeniable best in that role and if you have that attitude
you are going to be the absolute best that you can be
if you remember this concept and put it in play
you cannot ever lose
[Music] it doesn't matter where you come from it
doesn't matter what your background is it doesn't matter what race you are what
gender you are it doesn't matter who your parents are
dude we can make every excuse in the book
but i promise you for every excuse you can make there are
literally thousands of people who had it harder than you that have
done what the you want to do there is nothing that can stop you
when you become so skilled that every single person around you sees that and
it recognizes that and that is a habit
that is not a gift that is something that you can create
it's a skill you can learn so develop the skill of becoming undeniable if you
remember this concept and put it in play you cannot ever lose
[Music]